Welcome back. https://youtu.be/LEkRzeVJTwU
Chào mừng trở lại https://youtu.be/LEkRzeVJTwU
As I promised I&#39;m going to go to website, and I would encourage you to look at it.
Như tôi đã hứa, Tôi sẽ ghé thăm trang web mà tôi đã khuyến khích mọi người vào xem.
So I&#39;m going to portend the symbol for Amazon, which is AMZN.
Tôi sẽ gõ tắt trang Amazon thành AMZN
And we&#39;ll go to that page.
và chúng ta sẽ đi đến trang đó.
And if you notice on the first page, you have Amazon&#39;s data available,
Nếu bạn để ý thì ở ngay đầu trang chủ, bạn có thể thấy các thông tin có sẵn trên Amazon
you have the stock price which is 738.
Bạn có thể thấy giá cổ phiếu là 738
It just changed from 738.9 to .95,
Giá chỉ nhích từ 738.9 lên .95
previous close 736.
trước đó thì đạt gần 736.
I would encourage you to go right now,
Tôi khuyến khích bạn vào xem trang ngay lúc này
obviously you are at different time watching at different times you can go and
Hiển nhiên bạn có thể ghé thăm trang bất cứ thời điểm nào bạn có thể
some of the information I&#39;m going to talk about is pretty much available
và một số thông tin tôi định đề cập đã có gần hết ở đây rồi
over here and I just show you this is the pre-disclosed risk today.
Tôi sẽ cho các bạn thấy, đây là các chỉ số dự trước rủi ro hôm nay
I am taping today so the days are different for you.
Tôi đang ấn vào hôm nay, cho nên ngày tháng có thể thay đổi theo ý bạn chọn.
Bid ask prices, open price, day range, volume, average volume.
Giá mua vào- giá bán ra, giá mở cửa, phạm vi dao động giá trong ngày, khối lượng giao dịch, khối lượng giao dịch trung bình.
And then I&#39;m going to press Statistics.
tiếp theo tôi nhấn vào phần thống kê.
And if you go to Statistics, you&#39;ll see,
nếu bạn vào phần này, bạn có thể thấy một vài số liệu
start seeing some numbers that I&#39;m going to show you and one is market cap.
Tôi sẽ chỉ cho các bạn, hàng đầu tiên là giá trị vốn hóa thị trường.
So when you see market cap it shows 300, right now it shows about
Khi bạn thấy phần này ghi 300, bây giờ thì ghi nhận khoảng 348$.
$348 billion which is the market cap of Amazon, all right.
348 tỉ $ chính là giá trị vốn hóa thị trường của Amazon.
And I&#39;ll keep going down this price book, price, sales If you keep scrolling down,
Tôi sẽ lướt xuống phần giá cổ phiếu/ giá ghi sổ sách,  giá cổ phiếu/doanh số. Nếu các bạn tiếp tục kéo xuống,
I would encourage you to look for
Các bạn nên chú ý phần
a balance sheet item and you&#39;ll see total debt.
bảng cân đối kế toán, bạn có thể thấy tổng nợ.
And right now if I go down I see debt of about 17.61 billion.
Bây giờ khi tôi kéo xuống, chúng ta có thể thấy phần tổng nợ vào khoảng 17.61 tỉ.
So the reason I&#39;m focusing on this is, Amazon, I can go there,
Lí do mà tôi nhấn mạnh vào điều này là tôi có thể vào trang và
look up its balance sheet numbers, and I&#39;m going to ask you the following question.
tìm kiếm các số liệu bảng cân đối kế toán của amazon. Tôi sẽ hỏi các bạn câu sau.
Right now, Amazon&#39;s total market cap,
tổng giá trị vốn hóa thương mại của Amazon
which is price times number of shares, is about $350 billion.
chính là giá trị của số lượng cổ phiếu tại các thời điểm nhất định, ngay lúc này rơi vào khoảng 350$
And its debt is about $17 billion.
và số nợ của Amazon là khoảng 17 tỉ đô
So, what assumption can you approximately safely make about Amazon?
Từ đây bạn có thể đưa ra được nhận định khá chắc chắn nào về Amazon?
Let&#39;s assume that Amazon has only equity financing.
Giả sử Amazon chỉ huy động nguồn quỹ từ kênh chủ sở hữu
Okay, so what has happened?
vậy điều gì xảy ra?
Debt you can assume close to zero so that return on assets and
Khi bạn giả định nợ gần như bằng không thì hệ số thu nhập trên tài sản và
return on equity will be the same.
hệ số lợi nhuận ròng trên vốn chủ sở hữu là như nhau.
So that&#39;s what I wanted to show you right now and when we come back later,
Đó chính là điều tôi muốn bạn nhận ra lúc này, và khi chúng ta trở lại
I&#39;ll also show you some other information on the Amazon page.
Tôi sẽ trình bày những thông tin khác trên trang Amazon.
Meanwhile, whenever you have a chance, whether it&#39;s Amazon or so on as I&#39;ve said
Khi bạn có thời gian, không chỉ về Amazon mà còn những cái khác như tôi đã đề cập trong giáo án
in my syllabus too, go too Yahoo Finance and try to figure things out.
hãy vào trang Yahoo Finance và thử tìm hiểu về mọi thứ.
So I&#39;ve shown you a balance sheet, what have I shown you?
Tôi đã chỉ cho các bạn về bảng cân đối kế toán. Tôi còn chỉ cho các bạn những gì nữa?
The total market value of equity of Amazon is about 350 billion,
Tổng giá trị thị trường vốn chủ sở hữu của Amazon là khoảng 350 tỉ
which is also almost perfectly close, not quite,
con số này gần như bằng với
to the total market value of all its assets.
tổng giá trị thị trường toàn bộ tài sản của Amazon.
So if I asked you what;s the value of Amazon, you&#39;ll say $350 billion.
Vậy nên khi tôi hỏi bạn về giá trị của Amazon, bạn sẽ trả lời là 350 tỉ $.
It&#39;s technically more right, because it&#39;s equity plus debt, but
điều này, về cơ bản là đúng. Vì tài sản bằng vốn chủ sở hữu cộng với nợ phải trả
the debt is very small.
Tuy nhiên khoản nợ lại rất nhỏ.
That&#39;s one of the reasons why I&#39;ve also chosen Amazon is when we come back
Đó là một trong những lí do tại sao tôi chọn Amazon, khi chúng ta trở lại
later what will we see?
Chúng ta sẽ thấy điều gì?
The return on equity of Amazon, and return on assets of Amazon are the same.
hệ số thu nhập trên tài sản và hệ số lợi nhuận ròng trên vốn chủ sở hữu là như nhau.
Point number one.
Luận điểm thứ nhất.
Please remember that.
Xin hãy nhớ cho.
The critical issue is once I figure that return on assets for Amazon, when
Điều then chốt ở đây là khi tôi suy ra hệ số thu nhập trên tài sản của Amazon.
we come back to this site, after you&#39;ve done some work, I want to set it up.
Chúng ta sẽ trở lại trang này, sau khi các bạn làm xong một số việc, tôi muốn hệ thống lại các thứ
Is that return on asset becomes the return on assets for
Có phải hệ số thu nhập trên tài khoản đó cũng chính là hệ số thu nhập trên tài sản
home, for rain forest, my new idea.
home, for rain forest, my new idea.
Remember the purpose to go to Amazon was try to figure out
hãy nhớ mục đích chúng ta vào Amazon là để tìm hiểu về
what are the cost of capital for rain forest.
what are the cost of capital for rain forest.
So, why did I go to Amazon?
Tại sao chúng ta vào Amazon?
Bottom line, whenever you&#39;re thinking of cost of capital,
Dòng cuối, bất cứ khi nào bạn nghĩ về chi phí sử dụng vốn
it doesn&#39;t belong to you as a manager, it belongs to the marketplace.
Chi phí này không thuộc về bạn với tư cách nhà quản lí, nó thuộc về sàn giao dịch điện tử
Another way to think about it is the following.
Bạn có thể nghĩ theo cách sau đây
There&#39;s an investor to whom you&#39;ll go and ask, not just one,
There&#39;s an investor to whom you&#39;ll go and ask, not just one,
of probably many people.
of probably many people.
And you&#39;ll go and ask for money.
bạn đến và xin họ đầu tư tiền.
What are they going to think?
Họ sẽ nghĩ gì?
They aren&#39;t gonna think like you as a project manager,
Họ sẽ không nghĩ giống cách của bạn - một quản lý dự án
they&#39;re going to think like a investor.
họ sẽ nghĩ theo cách của nhà đầu tư
And what does the investor do?
Vậy nhà đầu tư sẽ làm gì?
An investor will shop around.
Họ sẽ dò xét khắp nơi
An investor will say wait a second,
Và bảo bạn đợi
rain forest is going into an online portal selling everything.
rain forest sẽ vào một cổng thông tin điện tử trực tuyến nơi bán mọi thứ
A-ha!
A-ha!
So who&#39;s likely to be a smaller compatible as we call them?
So who&#39;s likely to be a smaller compatible as we call them?
Amazon.
Amazon.
So let&#39;s figure out what rate of return Amazon is providing.
Hãy tìm hiểu lợi suất mà Amazon mang lại
If you provide a higher rate of return than Amazon what will I do?
Nếu lợi suất bạn mang lại cao hơn Amazon thì tôi sẽ làm gì?
I&#39;ll invest in you.
Tôi sẽ đầu tư vào bạn.
If you provide a rate of return below Amazon, what will I do?
Còn nếu bạn đem lại lợi suất thấp hơn Amazon?
I will not give you the money.
Tôi sẽ không đưa tiền cho bạn đâu.
In fact, you shouldn&#39;t put your own money.
Sư thật là bạn không nên sử dụng tiền của mình
You should give it to Amazon.
Hãy đầu tư số tiền đó vào amazon
So comparable is same business and the return on the alternative
So comparable is same business and the return on the alternative
is why everything is relative pricing, is what is your cost of capital,
is why everything is relative pricing, is what is your cost of capital,
because that&#39;s what you&#39;ve got to beat to convince people to join you.
because that&#39;s what you&#39;ve got to beat to convince people to join you.
We&#39;re going to take a break.
We&#39;re going to take a break.
I would like you to just explore Amazon&#39;s website and look at data.
I would like you to just explore Amazon&#39;s website and look at data.
I promise you, once we have done risk and return and understood how to calculate Re
I promise you, once we have done risk and return and understood how to calculate Re
and Ra, we will go back and revisit this interesting problem.
and Ra, we will go back and revisit this interesting problem.
See you soon.
hẹn gặp lại